The arch of his career was like that of an eagle taking flight.
他的事业曲线犹如一只雄鹰展翅飞翔。
People have said that what Sinatra was to the 1940s, Elvis to the 1950s, the Beatles
人们说，辛纳屈是20世纪40年代的，猫王是50年代，甲壳虫乐队
to the 60s, John Denver was to the 1970s.
到60年代，约翰·丹佛（John Denver）是1970年代的代表。
His music was powerful and his message was so positive and compassionate.
他的音乐充满力量，他的信息是如此积极和富有同情心。
It's refreshing to hear it again today.
今天再次听到它是令人耳目一新的。
John always talked about coming back as an eagle.
约翰总是谈论着以雄鹰的身份归来。
You know it's an incredibly difficult song to sing.
你知道这是一首难以想象的难唱的歌。
The notes he has to hit, but it's brilliant in terms of the personification of the animal.
他必须击中每一个音符，但在动物的拟人化方面非常出色。
If any song would be John's profile, it would be the eagle in the heart.
如果有任何歌曲能代表约翰，那将是心中的雄鹰。
Because I think he saw himself as that.
因为我认为他把自己看作是那样的人。
That's why he always wanted to fly.
这就是为什么他总是想要飞翔。
Sometimes when I would rehearse the orchestra before he would come in and you would get
有时候，在他进来之前，当我排练交响乐团时，
this kind of crusty symphony orchestra and they were all kind of a little upset that
这种脾气暴躁的交响乐团，他们都有点不高兴，
they're doing a pop concert.
因为他们在举办一场流行音乐会。
And then John would come in and start singing and lonely hope and smiles would start to
然后约翰会进来，开始唱歌，孤独的希望，微笑将开始
appear.
出现。
And all of a sudden you would catch the first violinist kind of tapping his foot or her
突然之间，您会抓住第一个小提琴家，敲打他的脚或她
foot and suddenly they would like, oh, you know.
脚，突然他们想要，哦，你知道。
From a performing standpoint, working with John every night on stage was like being in
从表演的角度来看，每晚在舞台上与约翰一起工作就像在
school with a master.
学校和一位大师一起工作。
Nobody could work an audience like John Denver.
没有人能像约翰·丹佛这样的观众工作。
People are always asking me, hey, how come you're so relaxed on stage?
人们总是问我，嘿，你怎么这么放松在舞台上？
I said I have the best teacher at John Denver.
我说我有约翰·丹佛最好的老师。
It's how I'm going to be myself on stage.
这就是我将在舞台上成为自己的方式。
It was quite an experience for all of us, the band members and the wives and my friends
这对我们所有人，乐队成员和妻子和我的朋友来说都是一个很大的经历
and all of our friends watching John make the transition from a well-known singer, songwriter
我们所有观看约翰的朋友都看到他从一位著名歌手，词曲作者过渡到
to a household name.
家喻户晓的名字。
Woo-hoo!
哇！
Thank God I'm a hundred more years old!
感谢上帝，我还有一百岁！
John Denver had a profound effect on so many of us.
约翰·丹佛（John Denver）对我们许多人产生了深远的影响。
Several years after his death, we, his friends, are able to speak about him.
他去世几年后，我们的朋友们能够谈论他。
I can't remember not singing.
我不记得不唱歌的时候。
Evidently from the time I could first talk, I started repeating the songs that I heard
显然，从我第一次讲话的那一刻起，我就开始重复我
on the radio.
在广播里听到的歌曲。
And they called me Jitterbug as a matter of fact.
事实上他们称我为Jitterbug。
I think that's because that was kind of the popular music form at the time.
我认为这是因为当时那是一种流行的音乐形式。
And my grandmother gave me a guitar when I was 12 years old.
我12岁那年，我的祖母给了我吉他。
It was a guitar that she had played in her younger years.
这是她年轻时弹的吉他。
And I got the guitar out and I let her pick around on it.
我拿出吉他，让她弹奏。
And he just tried to sing up a storm.
他只是尽力唱得热情洋溢。
He was singing a little nursery rhyme songs at the time.
当时他正在唱一些童谣。
And I said, John, I said, would you practice if mom would give you music lessons?
而我说，约翰，我说，如果妈妈给你上音乐课，你会练习吗？
I said, if you will, Grandma will give you this guitar.
我说，如果您愿意，奶奶会给您这吉他。
So he asked his mom and she says, if you'll practice.
所以他问妈妈，她说，如果你会练习。
So I gave him the guitar and that's where he is today.
所以我给了他吉他，这成就了今天的他。
When John first walked into the audition with a smile as white as his face,
当约翰第一次带着一张白得像他脸庞一样的微笑走进试镜时，
I was immediately attracted.
我立即被吸引。
And I was won over completely.
而我完全被征服了。
It became, you know, probably the strongest relationship I ever had in music.
这变成了，你知道，可能是我在音乐中曾经拥有的最牢固的关系。
I worked with him, you know, from four days after his audition to the day he died.
我和他一起工作，你知道，从他试镜后的四天到他去世的那天。
And felt closer to him than anybody.
我觉得比任何人都更亲近他。
Leaving on a jet plane was the song that really, to me,
乘着喷气飞机离开这首歌对我来说确实是
opened the door for his career and what would follow.
为他的事业打开了大门，并引领了后来的发展。
That was a great song. It was a timely song.
那是一首很棒的歌。这是一首及时的歌。
A lot of people didn't know he had written it.
很多人不知道他已经写了。
The first time I heard Leaving on a Jetplane, I was at in Minneapolis at an auditorium
我第一次听到离开喷气式飞机时，我在明尼阿波利斯的礼堂里
that John was doing a sound check in.
约翰正在进行声音检查。
He was with a group called the Chad Mitchell Trio.
他与一个名为Chad Mitchell三人组的小组在一起。
He was standing by himself in this auditorium and he was singing Leaving on a Jetplane.
他独自站在礼堂里，唱着乘着喷气飞机离开。
It was really beautiful. It was crystal clear.
真的很漂亮。这很清楚。
John had this crystalline quality to his voice.
约翰的声音具有这种结晶的品质。
That was the first time I ever heard it.
那是我第一次听到它。
I think the first real impact that his stardom had on me was when I did the first live concert with him.
我认为他成名对我的第一次真正的影响是在我与他一起进行的第一场现场音乐会上。
John came out and started performing and the crowd just went wild.
约翰出来开始表演，人群刚刚疯狂。
That was my first realization that he had something that was magical with all these people.
那是我第一次意识到，他对所有这些人都有一种神奇的东西。
I would look out at the audience and they were people of all ages.
我会看着观众，他们是各个年龄段的人。
All my bags are packed. I'm ready to go.
我的行李都打包好了，我准备好要走了。
I understand in here I'm trying to go.
我了解在这里我想去。
I hate to wake you up and say goodbye.
我讨厌叫醒你，说再见。
But the dawn is breaking. It's early morning.
但黎明即将到来，现在是清晨。
He heard Peter Polin marry rendition of Leaving on a Jetplane
他听到彼得·波林 (Peter Polin) 演唱了《乘坐喷气式飞机离开》(Leaving on a Jetplane)
and he heard it for the first time on the car radio.
他是第一次在汽车收音机上听到的。
He practically had to drive off the road to get away, to stop the car. He was so excited.
他几乎不得不驶出路来，停下车。他太兴奋了。
Tell me that you wait for me. Hold me like you never let me go.
告诉我你在等我。抱着我，就像你永远不会让我走。
The end of a summer tour we were in Boston playing the Harbor Lights right down on the water
夏季巡回演出的结尾，我们在波士顿在水面上播放港口灯
and right near Logan International Airport.
就在洛根国际机场附近。
So Plains kept going overhead and he starts the song.
于是飞机持续飞过头顶，他开始唱歌。
And a jet comes taking off and it's so loud we can't hear anything.
飞机起飞，发出巨大的噪音，我们什么都听不见。
So he starts again and he keeps doing this.
因此，他再次开始，他继续这样做。
At one point Chris Knoll the piano player had this keyboard and he had a jetplane sound in there
钢琴演奏家克里斯·诺尔（Chris Knoll）有一个键盘，里面有飞机的声音。
and he cranked it up and still the whole of the gear was blooming with the jetplane.
然后他把音量调得很大，整个演出设备都充满了飞机的声音。
Cause I'm leaving on a jetplane.
因为我要乘坐喷气式飞机离开。
Don't know when I'll be back again.
不知道什么时候我再回来。
Oh babe I hate to go.
哦，宝贝，我不愿离开。
There's so many times I've let you down.
有很多次让你失望。
So many times I've played around.
我玩弄了很多次。
I tell you now they don't need a thing.
我告诉你，他们不需要任何东西。
Every place I go I'll think of you.
我去的每个地方我都会想到你。
Every song I sing I'll sing for you.
我唱歌的每首歌都会为你唱歌。
When I come back I'll bring your wedding ring.
当我回来时，我会带上你的结婚戒指。
So kiss me and smile for me.
所以亲吻我，为我微笑。
Tell me that you'll wait for me.
告诉我，你会等我。
Hold me like you never.
像你一样抱着我。
And John sang the song for me before we recorded it.
约翰在录制之前为我演唱了这首歌。
And I liked everything about it except the name of the song.
我喜欢这首歌的一切，除了歌名。
And I said oh babe I hate to go.
我说哦，宝贝，我不愿离开。
John that's kind of a bland title that's hard to remember.
约翰，这个标题有点平淡，很难记住。
But you have a great line in the chorus leaving on a jetplane.
但你在副歌中有一句很棒的歌词，乘坐喷气式飞机离开。
Let's name it that.
就叫这个名字吧。
Cause I'm leaving on a jetplane.
因为我要乘坐喷气式飞机离开。
Don't know when I'll be back again.
不知道什么时候我再回来。
Oh babe I hate to go.
哦，宝贝，我不愿离开。
I'm leaving on a jetplane.
我要乘坐喷气式飞机离开。
Don't know when I'll be back again.
不知道什么时候我再回来。
Oh babe I hate to go.
哦，宝贝，我不愿离开。
If they know a western song in China they know Take Me Home Country Roads.
如果在中国有人知道一首西方歌曲，那一定是乡村路带我回家。
Take Me Home Country Roads actually was started by Bill Danoff and his wife Tathy.
乡村路带我回家实际上是由比尔·丹诺夫（Bill Danoff）和他的妻子塔西（Tathy）创作的。
And one night after John had performed we got together with Bill and Tathy and a group of musicians.
约翰演出的一个晚上，我们与Bill，Tathy和一群音乐家聚在一起。
And Bill had started Take Me Home Country Roads and they proceeded to play all night and they came up with this song.
比尔已经开始《Take Me Home, Country Roads》，他们整夜演奏，最后创作出了这首歌。
Almost heaven, West Virginia, Blue Ridge Mountains, Shenandoah River.
几乎天堂，西弗吉尼亚州，蓝岭山脉，谢南多厄河。
Life is older there, older than the trees, younger than the mountains, throwing like a breeze.
那里的生命更古老，比树木古老，比山年轻，像微风一样飘过
Country roads, Take Me Home to the place I belong.
乡村道路，带我回家我所属的地方。
Take Me Home Country Roads is a classic sing-along song.
乡村路带我回家是一首经典的歌曲。
It's an audience song.
这是一首观众歌。
It just fits into that great sort of tradition of a song that everybody sings and everybody wants to sing.
它只是融入了那种每个人都唱并且每个人都想唱的歌曲传统中。
You don't have to be the greatest singer in the world, you just sing that melody, just pour your heart into it.
你不必是世界上最伟大的歌手，你只需唱出那个旋律，将你的心灵倾注其中。
Dark and gusty, painted on the sky, misty taste of moonshine, tear drops in my eyes.
黑暗而狂风，画在天空上，月光的朦胧味道，泪滴落到我脸上。
It has become popular all over the world and surprisingly it was a very big song in China.
它在世界各地都流行，令人惊讶的是，它在中国是一首非常流行的歌曲。
And that came about when John did a concert at Constitution Hall in Washington.
那是约翰在华盛顿宪法大厅举行的音乐会时。
The President and the Premier of China were invited to John's concert.
总统和中国的总理被邀请参加约翰音乐会。
Afterwards, someone told me that the Premier wanted to take some cassettes of John's music back to China.
之后，有人告诉我，总理想把约翰音乐的一些录音带带回中国。
I asked how many cassettes he wanted and they said 500.
我问他想要多少个盒磁带，他们说500。
I hear her voice in the morning hour she calls me.
我早上就听到她打电话给我的声音。
Radio reminds me of my home far away.
收音机让我想起了我的家。
Driving down the road I get a feeling that I should have been home yesterday, yesterday.
沿着路开车，我有一种感觉，我昨天就应该回家了。
Country roads take me home to the place I belong.
乡村道路带我回家我所属的地方。
West Virginia, mountain mama, take me home. Country roads take me home.
西弗吉尼亚州，群山之母，带我回家。乡村路，带我回家。
That country roads take me home. Take me home. That country roads.
那条路带我回家。带我回家。那条乡间道路。
Years later, he said where can I go where I'm not known?
几年后，他说我可以去哪里我不认识的地方？
And he thought of China. He always wanted to go to China anyway.
他想到了中国。无论如何，他一直想去中国。
So he flew off to China assuming since he had never performed there, had never sold a record there,
因此，由于他从未在那儿演出，他在那里从未卖过唱片，
he could be relatively incognito.
他可能会相对不为人所知。
He gets off the plane in Shanghai and the way he described it,
他在上海下飞机，按照他的描述
dozens and dozens of people start gathering and pointing to him and people gather all,
数十人开始聚集并指向他，人们聚集在了一起，
John Denver, John Denver. And he couldn't quite understand it.
约翰·丹佛（John Denver），约翰·丹佛（John Denver）。而且他不太了解。
Turns out that the premier had wrote the cassettes and it sent them to all the radio stations in China
事实证明，总理带的磁带将它们送到了中国的所有广播电台
who weren't given permission to play western music except for this.
除了这首歌之外，他们没有获得演奏西方音乐的许可。
So Take Me Home Country Roads was played all over China.
因此，乡村路带我回家在整个中国播放。
It was Christmas 1970, Annie and I moved to Aspen.
那是1970年圣诞节，我和安妮搬到了阿斯彭。
Mountain promontories had always been part of the equation for us
对我们来说，山地的海角一直是我们考虑的一部分
and when the numbers for country roads kept growing, I figured we could afford our dream house.
当乡村道路的数字不断增长时，我认为我们能负担得起我们梦寐以求的房子。
We thought it was beautiful and we could live any place.
我们觉得这是美好的，我们可以住在任何地方。
After he'd spent the whole winter out here, we decided to move and we pulled into Aspen.
在他度过了整个冬天之后，我们决定搬家，然后进入阿斯彭。
It was a great time.
这是一个伟大的时刻。
I'll never forget John was on the road and I pulled in and I thought,
我永远不会忘记约翰在路上，我坐了进去，我想，
oh my gosh, we're really home.
哦，天哪，我们真的回家了。
He's a finder's all you know.
他是您所知道的。
Winter's cold, Aspen's cold.
冬天很冷，阿斯彭很冷。
Aspen is a life to live.
阿斯彭是生活的生活。
See how much there is to give.
看看要付出多少
See how strongly you believe.
看看你坚信多么坚强。
See how much you may receive.
看看你可能会收到多少。
Smiling faces all around.
周围都是微笑。
Laughter is the only sound.
笑声是唯一的声音。
Memories that can't grow old.
记忆永不会变老。
Winter's cold, Aspen's cold.
冬天很冷，阿斯彭也很冷。
John's feeling for the earth and the environment was so strong,
约翰对地球和环境的感觉是如此强烈，
it really colors his music and his lyrics.
这确实为他的音乐和歌词增色。
We learn in the presence of other generations.
我们在其他几代人面前学到了东西。
The old need to teach the young and the young need to teach the old.
老人需要教年轻人，年轻人也需要教老人。
Although I'm no less distressed about the earth's needs than when I was younger,
尽管我对地球的需求感到的困扰不亚于年轻时，
I see more clearly now what I can do about it and I see that it needs doing
我现在更清楚地看到了我能为此做些什么，我也看到这是必须要做的
as I live my life daily and reverently.
当我每天虔诚地过着生活时。
This isn't the reverence of the holier than thou.
这不是崇敬的表现，而是一种虔诚的生活方式。
It's the reverence that says, do thyself no harm, for we are all here together.
这是一种说：“不要伤害自己”的敬畏，因为我们都在这里。
John leave, breath through nature and that's why he found his inspiration.
约翰通过大自然呼吸，这就是他找到灵感的原因。
He spent a long time on the bow of Carripsa.
他在Carripsa号的船头度过了很长时间。
He was so touched and taken by the experience that he had had
他对自己的经历感到如此感动和震撼
that he spent several hours composing.
以至于他花了几个小时进行创作。
He was composing in his head and that's where Carripsa was born.
他在脑海中进行创作，Carripsa就是在那里诞生的。
The kind of the growing, the kind of the today, you understand.
成长的方式，今天的方式，你明白。
I act a little so the places you've been to, things that you've shown us,
我有点行动，所以你去过的地方，你向我们展示的东西，
the stories you tell.
以及你讲的故事。
I act a little so I sing to your spirit, the band you have served,
我有点行动，所以我为你的精神唱歌，你曾经服务的那支乐队，
the song you've sung so long and so well.
你唱得如此之久，如此之好的那首歌。
I am here, I am here, I am here, I am here.
我在这里，我在这里，我在这里，我在这里。
It was definitely a high point energy wise in the concert.
从能源角度来看，这绝对是音乐会中的一个高潮。
He would just go right up into those high notes and he just could belt them out
他会直接走到那些高音上，然后他就会高声演唱，
and I think the audience was just sitting there saying, this is great, this is great.
我认为观众只是坐在那里说，这太棒了，太棒了。
I could go through the guides you bring us beside you
我可以通过你给我们带来的向导
to light up the darkness and show us the way.
点燃黑暗并向我们展示道路。
What Calypso did for the Cousteau Society is enormous.
对于库斯托社会来说，卡里普索的贡献是巨大的。
Outside of the fact that John donated all the royalties of the song to the society,
除了约翰将歌曲的所有特许权使用费捐赠给社会之外
he really gave people in the world an awareness of what Jacou Stowe is doing.
他确实为世界上的人们增加了对Jacou Stowe所做事情的认识。
It's the time, the free airs of winter, the doors of love, this wedding is in the sea.
现在是时候，冬天的自由气息，爱的大门，这场婚礼在海中。
I act a little so the places you've been to, the things that you've shown us, the stories you tell.
我有点行动，所以你去过的地方，你向我们展示的东西，你讲的故事。
I act a little so I sing to your spirit, the venue has served us so long and so well.
我有点行动，所以我为你的精神唱歌，场地为我们服务了这么长时间。
I act a little so the places you've been to, the things that you've shown us, the stories you tell.
我有点行动，所以你去过的地方，你向我们展示的东西，你讲的故事。
I act a little so I sing to your spirit, the venue has served us so long and so well.
我有点行动，所以我为你的精神唱歌，场地为我们服务了这么长时间。
To me John taught all of us great lessons on how to respect and love nature.
对我来说，约翰教给我们所有人如何尊重和热爱大自然的重要教训。
And it was based on his curiosity, his desire to understand and know.
这是基于他的好奇心，他对理解和认识的渴望。
He did it because he had to do it.
他这样做是因为内心驱使。
My personal urgent moral concern for the planet Earth found expression.
我个人对地球的紧急道德关切得以表达。
In it, mixed into my own thought, I could hear Buckminster Fuller's moral vocabulary and Jacou Stowe's
在其中，混入我的思维中，我能听到巴克明斯特·富勒（Buckminster Fuller）的道德词汇和雅克·斯托（Jacou Stowe）的
and Amory Lovens and that of a dozen others who are real stewards of the Earth.
还有阿莫里·洛夫斯（Amory Lovens）以及其他十几位真正的地球管理者。
My performance tours thereafter were conceived less as ends in themselves
此后，我的演出巡演不再仅仅是为了表演本身
and more as an ongoing effort to celebrate the Earth as home.
更多地是一种持续努力，庆祝地球作为家园。
You know I've said before that John was a real complicated guy.
你知道我以前说过，约翰是一个真正复杂的人。
I think he had big mood swings.
我认为他的情绪波动很大。
He could be totally elated in the very down in the dumps.
在最低谷时他可能会感到非常高兴。
But I think that that's kind of that artistic temperament.
但我认为那是一种艺术气质。
And yet when the music would come out of him, I think it came out of that very universal place that all of us experience.
然而，当音乐从他身上涌现时，我认为它来自我们所有人都经历过的那个非常普遍的地方。
The Sunshine of My Shoulders is a beautiful song.
我肩膀的阳光是一首美丽的歌。
And when you hear him sing it, it's just pure honesty in his voice.
当您听到他唱歌时，他的声音只是纯粹的诚实。
That was probably one of his greatest gifts of all, is he could be so honest when he sang a song.
那可能是他所有伟大才华之一，他在唱歌时能如此真实。
I think it was really about his feeling of being outdoors, Colorado.
我认为这确实是关于他对户外，科罗拉多州的感觉。
Sunshine of My Shoulders makes me happy. It's a simple kind of childlike verse.
我肩膀的阳光让我开心。这是一种简单的童话诗。
I had written the song in a fit of melancholy, one wet and dismal late winter, early spring day in Minnesota.
我以忧郁的心情，一个潮湿而令人沮丧的冬季，明尼苏达州的早春末期写了这首歌。
On one level it was about the virtues of love.
在一个层面上，这是关于爱的美德。
On another, more deeply felt level, it reached out for something the whole world could embrace.
在另一个更深的水平上，它伸出了全世界所能拥抱的东西。
Sunshine makes me happy. Sunshine almost always makes me high.
阳光让我快乐。阳光几乎总是让我陶醉。
If I had a day that I could give you, I'd give to you a day just like today.
如果我有一天可以给你的一天，我会像今天一样给你一天。
I mean, it's beautiful and I think that's how we all feel.
我的意思是，这很漂亮，我认为这就是我们所有人的感受。
If I had a song that I could sing for you
如果我有一首可以为你唱歌的歌
I'd sing a song to make you feel this way.
我会唱一首歌，让你有这种感觉。
I think that song can be sung either joyously or sadly.
我认为那首歌可以喜悦或悲伤地演唱。
You know, he did it in that slow version, which I found very, very moving.
你知道，他以缓慢的版本做到了这一点，我发现这非常非常动人。
Hidden inside that positive message, there's some pain in there in that song.
隐藏在那个积极信息中，那首歌里有一些痛苦。
Sunshine in my eyes can make me cry.
我眼中的阳光会让我哭泣。
Sunshine on the water looks so lovely.
水上的阳光看起来很可爱。
Sunshine almost always makes me high.
阳光几乎总是让我陶醉。
Sunshine almost all the time makes me high.
Sunshine almost always.
阳光几乎总是。
Music plays
音乐播放
He said, Lee, I've got this new song, you know, Milt loves it.
他说，李，我知道这首新歌，你知道，米尔特喜欢它。
We're going to record it.
我们将记录下来。
Let me play it for you.
让我为你演奏。
So he picked up the guitar and played Annie's song.
因此，他拿起吉他并演奏了安妮的歌。
Played it perfectly, top to bottom.
完美的演绎，从头到尾。
And he looked at me and he said, what do you think we should do with this song?
然后他看着我说：“你觉得我们该怎么处理这首歌呢？”
And I just looked at him and said, we should just do that.
我只是看着他说，我们应该这样做。
Just what you just did.
正是你刚刚做的。
I know Milt is fond of saying there are four or five songs that people use for weddings.
我知道米尔特（Milt）喜欢说人们在婚礼上使用了四到五首歌曲。
And he says, Wagner has one and John Denver has two.
他说，瓦格纳有一个，约翰·丹佛有两个。
I've heard Annie's song with the strolling violins in St. Mark's Square in Venice.
我在威尼斯的圣马克广场（St. Mark's Square）听过安妮（Annie）的歌曲。
I heard it in an elevator in Japan.
我在日本的一台电梯里听到了它。
I've heard it.
我听到了。
I'm just struck when I hear it.
每次听到这首歌，我都为之震撼。
And it's not, I have to tell you, I don't connect with it as me anymore.
告诉你，我不再将它视为属于我的东西。
I mean, I did it one time, but it's become so much bigger than that.
我的意思是，我曾经这样认为，但现在它变得比那更为重要。
But the most beautiful time I ever heard it was last summer when my daughter was married.
但我听到它最美丽的时刻是去年夏天我女儿结婚的时候。
And she married somebody that John actually had the opportunity to get to know before he died.
她嫁给了约翰在他去世之前实际上有机会了解的人。
I wrote Annie's song, writing up in a ski lift one day.
我写了安妮（Annie）的歌，有一天写在滑雪缆车上。
When suddenly I was hypersensitive to how beautiful everything was.
突然间，我对周围一切有多美变得非常敏感。
The sky was a blue you only see from mountaintops.
天空是一种只有站在山巅才能看到的蓝色。
Then I became aware of the other people skiing, the colors of their clothes, the birds singing,
接着我注意到其他滑雪的人，他们衣服的颜色，鸟儿在唱歌，
the sound of the lift, the sibilant sound of the skiers going down the mountain.
缆车的声音，滑雪者下山时的嘶嘶声。
All of these things filled up my senses.
所有这一切充满了我的感官。
And when I said this to myself, unbidden images came one after the other.
当我对自己说这句话时，画面一个接一个地涌现。
The night in the forest, a walk in the rain, the mountains in springtime.
森林里的夜晚，雨中漫步，春天的山脉。
All of the pictures merged, and then what I was left with was Annie.
所有的画面融为一体，然后我所剩下的就是安妮。
That song was the embodiment of the love that I felt at the time.
那首歌是我当时感受到的爱的具体表达。
You fill up my senses like a night in a forest.
你充满我的感官，就像森林中的夜晚。
Like the mountains in springtime, like a walk in the rain.
就像春天的山脉，如雨中漫步。
Like a storm in the desert, like a sleepy blue ocean.
就像沙漠中的风暴，如昏昏欲睡的蓝色海洋。
You fill up my senses, come fill me again.
你充满了我的感官，再次填满我。
Come let me love you, let me give my life to you.
来吧，让我爱你，让我把我的生命献给你。
Let me drown in your laughter, let me die in your arms.
让我沉浸在你的笑声中，让我死在你的怀中。
Let me lay down beside you, let me always be with you.
让我躺在你身旁，让我永远陪伴着你。
Come let me love you, I'll love me again.
来吧，让我爱你，我会再次爱自己。
Come let me give my life to you.
快来，让我把我的生命献给你。
Come let me love you, come love me again.
来吧，让我爱你，再次爱我。
You fill up my senses like a night in a forest.
你充满我的感官，就像森林中的夜晚。
Like the mountains in springtime, like a walk in the rain.
就像春天的山脉，如雨中漫步。
Like a storm in the desert, like a sleepy blue ocean.
就像沙漠中的风暴，如昏昏欲睡的蓝色海洋。
You fill up my senses, come fill me again.
你充满了我的感官，再次填满我。
The first song of John's that impressed me so much with his maturity for a young 22 or 23 year old
约翰的第一首歌给我留下了深刻的印象，他的成熟年轻22岁或23岁
was Rhymes and Reasons. I just couldn't believe the lyric for the children and the flowers of my sisters and my brothers.
是押韵和原因。我简直不敢相信孩子们的抒情诗，我的姐妹和兄弟的花朵。
Their laughter and their loveliness would clear a cloudy day.
他们的笑声和可爱将驱散乌云。
Like the music of the mountains and the colors of the rainbow, they're a promise of the future and a blessing for the day.
就像山脉的音乐和彩虹的颜色一样，它们是对未来的承诺，也是一天的祝福。
So you speak to me of sadness, the coming of the winter.
因此，您向我谈论悲伤，冬天的到来。
Fear that is within you now, seems to never end.
担心现在在你里面，似乎永无止境。
And the dreams that have escaped you, the hope that you've forgotten.
逃脱了你的梦想，你已经忘记的希望。
You tell me that you need me now, you want to be my friend.
你告诉我你现在需要我，你想成为我的朋友。
And you wonder where we're going, where's the rhyme, where's the reason.
你会想知道我们要去哪里，找不到韵律，找不到理由。
And it's you cannot accept, it is here we must begin to seek the wisdom of the children.
您不能接受，在这里我们必须开始寻求孩子的智慧。
And the graceful way of flowers in the wind.
以及风中花朵的优雅方式。
I'd learned that powerful songs are powerful not because they're pretty or bouncy or funny,
我了解到，歌曲之所以强有力，并不是因为它们漂亮、有弹性或有趣
but because they're about the human condition and what we all aspire to.
而是因为它们是关于人类状况以及我们都渴望的。
I'd learned those were the songs I loved.
我知道那是我喜欢的歌。
They clear a cloudy day. Like the music of the mountains and the colors of the rainbow,
他们清除了阴天。就像山脉的音乐和彩虹的颜色一样，
they're a promise of the future and a blessing for today.
它们是对未来的承诺，也是今天的祝福。
One of my favorite singers was Jacques Brel.
我最喜欢的歌手之一是雅克·布雷尔（Jacques Brel）。
And I introduced Jacques Brel's records to John, who immediately caught on to how good and how important a writer Brel was.
我将雅克·布雷尔（Jacques Brel）的唱片介绍给约翰（John），后者立即了解了作家布雷尔（Brel）的重要性和重要性。
And it was interesting, one of the French critics said, it seems to me that John Denver is to America what Jacques Brel is to us.
一位法国批评家说，这很有趣，在我看来，约翰·丹佛（John Denver）对美国来说，雅克·布雷尔（Jacques Brel）对我们来说是什么。
But he had a very big success in performance with Port of Amsterdam.
但是他在阿姆斯特丹港的表现取得了很大的成功。
In the Port of Amsterdam there's a sailor who sings of the dreams that he brings from the wide open sea.
在阿姆斯特丹港口，有一个水手唱着他从宽阔的公海带来的梦想。
In the Port of Amsterdam there's a sailor who sleeps while the river bank weeps to the old willow tree.
在阿姆斯特丹港口，有一个水手在河岸哭泣到旧柳树时睡觉。
John was definitely a showman and he would, he loved to put on a good concert and he knew that he could sing his balance,
约翰绝对是一名表演者，他会喜欢举办一场好音乐会，他知道自己可以唱平衡，
but he also needed to do his lighthearted, funny songs as well.
但是他也需要做他轻松的有趣的歌曲。
And he had to have a good mix of them and the audiences just seemed to just absolutely love that.
而且他必须很好地结合在一起，观众似乎绝对喜欢它。
Bands are like nothing else in life. Where singer-songwriters are concerned, the bonding takes the form of breathing together.
乐队在生活中别无其他。在涉及歌手兼作曲家的地方，纽带以呼吸的形式。
The people who are out there with you in front of an audience breathing with you while you are putting your life on the line are like none other.
与您一起在观众面前，与您一起呼吸的人们，在您将自己的生活置于危险之中，如同无人能及。
My first gig with John was actually The Tonight Show in about February of 1974.
我与约翰的第一次演出实际上是在1974年2月的《今晚秀》上。
And it was the first time that he had been invited to guest host The Tonight Show.
这是他第一次被邀请担任《今晚秀》嘉宾主持。
And that was a big shot for him.
这对他来说是一个重要时刻。
We'd be on stage in front of 30, 35,000 people. I mean, I couldn't believe it.
我们将站在3万到3.5万人的观众面前，我简直不敢相信。
And he realized right then and there and we all realized that we were, we had a huge tiger by the tail.
他就在那一刻意识到，我们所有人也意识到，我们握住了大老虎的尾巴。
And John was on his way to becoming a huge, huge star.
约翰正走在成为一位巨星的道路上。
John would always start off country boy with.
约翰总是以《乡村男孩》开始。
Alright everybody, 5 to your hands.
好的，每个人，拍手五次。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
Well a simple kind of life, never did me no harm.
好吧，一种简单的生活，从来没有任何伤害。
A race of me and family and working on a farm.
我和家人的种族，在农场工作。
Days are all filled with an easy country charm.
日子都充满了乡村魅力。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
Well I got me a fine life. I got me old fiddle.
好吧，我给了我美好的生活。我给了我旧小提琴。
When the sun's coming up I got cakes on the griddle.
当太阳升起时，我在烤架上拿了蛋糕。
Life ain't nothing but a bada-bada griddle.
生活不过是巴达 - 巴达烤肉。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
When the world's all round and the sun sets low.
当世界全面而太阳落下时。
I pull out my fiddle and I rise up to vote.
我掏出小提琴，我站起来投票。
Kids are all as sweet as a wad of people kind of love.
孩子们都像一个人的爱一样甜。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
I play a solid good in all things.
我在所有事情上都表现出色。
Good luck to Lord and my wife, but you're taking very good.
祝上帝和我的妻子好运，但你做得很好。
So I'll fiddle and I can work what they should.
所以我会摆弄，我可以努力工作。
Well thank God I'm a country boy.
谢谢上帝，我是一个乡下男孩。
Well I got me a fine life. I got me old fiddle.
好吧，我给了我美好的生活。我给了我老小提琴。
When the sun's coming up I got cakes on the griddle.
当太阳升起时，我在烤架上拿了蛋糕。
Life ain't nothing but a bada-bada griddle.
生活不过是巴达 - 巴达烤肉。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
Well I wouldn't trade my life for diamonds or jewels.
好吧，我不会将自己的生活换成钻石或珠宝。
There never was one of them money hungry fools.
从来没有一个饥饿的傻瓜。
They never had my fiddle and my plumbing tools.
他们从来没有我的小提琴和我的管道工具。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
The out city folk driving in a black limousine.
外出的城市民间驾驶黑色豪华轿车。
A lot of sad people thinkin' that's a mighty tune.
许多可悲的人认为这是一个强大的曲调。
Turnin' and entertaining on a deck, what I mean.
我的意思是在甲板上娱乐并在甲板上娱乐。
Well thank God I'm a country boy.
谢谢上帝，我是一个乡下男孩。
Well I got me a fine life. I got me old fiddle.
好吧，我给了我美好的生活。我给了我老小提琴。
When the sun's coming up I got cakes on the griddle.
当太阳升起时，我在烤架上拿了蛋糕。
Life ain't nothing but a bada-bada griddle.
生活不过是巴达 - 巴达烤肉。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
Woo!
哇！
So I'll fiddle when my dad is in the day he died.
所以当我父亲去世的那天，我会摆弄。
And I'll take my father hand and be close to the side.
我将握住父亲的手，靠近一边。
And if he lives a good life he'll sing a fiddle he cried.
如果他过着美好的生活，他会唱他哭的小提琴。
Well thank God you're a country boy.
好吧，感谢上帝，你是一个乡下男孩。
When my dad is up and young I'm gonna have to hide a letter.
当我父亲起床时，我将不得不隐藏一封信。
Talk to how the workers say his name on the fiddle.
谈谈工人如何在小提琴上说出他的名字。
Talk to how the women, how to give this a fiddle.
谈谈妇女如何给这个小提琴。
Well thank God I'm a country boy.
谢谢上帝，我是一个乡下男孩。
When the guys bein' fine I got me old fiddle.
当伙计们很好时，我给了我老小提琴。
When the sun's coming up I got cakes on the griddle.
当太阳升起时，我在烤架上拿了蛋糕。
Life ain't nothing but a bada-bada griddle.
生活不过是巴达 - 巴达烤肉。
Thank God I'm a country boy.
感谢上帝，我是一个乡村男孩。
Yes I am.
我是。
Music
音乐
Cheers
干杯
Music
音乐
Perhaps love is like a resting place, a shelter from the storm.
也许爱就像一个休息的地方，是暴风雨的庇护所。
John was very proud of his duet with Placido Domingo on Perhaps Love.
约翰为自己与Placido Domingo合唱的《也许爱》感到非常自豪。
I took it over to Placido Domingo's apartment and played it for him.
我把它拿到Placido Domingo的公寓给他听。
And then I got the idea of doing a duet even though no one said it could get radio play.
尽管没有人说它能在广播中播放，但我突发奇想要做一次二重奏。
The CBS, I think they call them Detail Men who bring the records around,
哥伦比亚广播公司的细节人员把它带到费城的FIL，
brought it to FIL in Philadelphia when the program director was out.
当时节目主管不在。
And the owner said, oh my wife is in love with him and she makes me go up to New York to hear him when everybody's at the Met.
店主说，哦，我的妻子爱上了他，她让我去纽约听到他的声音。
I'd love to hear that.
我很想听听。
He takes the LP in those days and puts it on and he can't play it.
所以他拿着LP，可当时他却无法播放。
The owner of one of the biggest stations in the country can't play a record.
这个国家最大的电台之一的老板无法播放这张唱片。
He said to his secretary, play it on so and so, you know, she can't get it played.
他对他的秘书说：“在某某地方播放它，她知道她不能播放。”
He says, ah, give it to the DJ, let him play it and I'll hear it over the air.
他说：“啊，给DJ，让他播放，我会在空中听到。”
So he put on his duet.
所以他戴上了二重奏。
The song is half over.
这首歌结束了一半。
The lights on the telephone switch would light up the hand.
电话开关上的灯光会照亮手。
Kaboom.
轰隆一声。
Perhaps love is like a resting place, a shelter from the storm.
也许爱就像一个休息的地方，是暴风雨的庇护所。
It exists to give you comfort, it is there to keep you warm.
它的存在是为了给您安慰，它可以使您保持温暖。
Of all of John's songs, that's probably my favorite.
在约翰的所有歌曲中，这可能是我的最爱。
It was written when John and I had decided to get a separation and then a divorce.
这是当我和约翰决定分居然后离婚时写的。
And so it was a difficult time in his life, my life, the lives of our friends, our family members.
因此，对他的一生，我的一生，我们的朋友和家人的生活来说，这是一个艰难的时期。
But John was on the road and he wrote the song and he sent it to me in an overnight letter.
但是约翰在旅途中，他写了这首歌并在一封隔夜信中寄给了我。
That last summer that he lived and he was being inducted into the song Writers Hall of Fame, it's the song he sang.
那是他生活的最后一个夏天，他被录为歌曲作家名人堂的成员，这是他唱的歌。
Oh, love for some's like a cloud, to some a straw is steel, for some a wave, for some a wave.
哦，爱对有些人如云，对有些人如稻草如钢，对有些人如浪花，对有些人如浪花。
I felt so much turmoil and I started to let it come out.
我感到非常混乱，我开始把它发泄出来。
I started thinking about all the ways I've experienced love, not that I was feeling very loved right then,
我开始思考我经历过的所有爱的方式，虽然当时我并没有感到被爱，
or that I had a love in my life anymore, but it was good to remember.
或者，我的生活已经有了爱，但是记住这是很好的。
I started remembering love and certain expressions of love and I tried to describe that.
我开始记住爱情和某些爱情的表达，并试图形容这一点。
I tried to describe all the ways that people think of love and how love is really all of those things
我试图描述人们想到爱的所有方式，以及爱实际上是所有这些事物
and these beautiful lines came pouring out of me.
这些美丽的诗句从我口中流淌而出。
If I should live forever, all my dreams come true.
如果我应该永远生活，我所有的梦想成真。
My memories of love will be of you.
我对爱的记忆将是你。
Last time I heard John sing was at a concert in the San Fernando Valley and he sang so beautifully that
上次我听说约翰·辛格（John Sing）是在圣费尔南多山谷（San Fernando Valley）的一场音乐会上
on the way back from the concert I said, John, since I've heard you, I never heard you sing as beautifully and as expressively as you did tonight.
在音乐会回来的路上我说：“约翰，自从我听到你以来，我从未听过你像今晚这样美丽和富有表现力的演唱。
And the audience reflected that. They were so wrapped and engrossed in,
观众反映了这一点。他们非常激动。
what are you doing? He said, you know, I owe it to Mr. Domingo.
你在干什么？他说，你知道，我欠多明哥先生。
When we record it, perhaps love, you call to my attention the way he colored his notes with the meaning of the word
当我们录制它时，你提到了他如何用音符的颜色来表达单词的含义
when he sang clouds, sounded like clouds, when he sang steel, it sounded like steel.
当他唱歌的云听起来像云时，当他唱歌时，听起来像钢。
So I started going through my songs and wherever there was a word that I could color the tone,
因此，我开始浏览我的歌曲，无论哪里有一个我可以为音调上色的词，
I found it just an interesting exercise and it works. Crowds love it.
我发现它只是一个有趣的练习，它起作用。人群喜欢它。
I want you to be very comfortable, enjoy yourselves, lay back and let yourself go wherever the music takes you.
我希望你感到非常舒适，尽情享受，放松自己，让音乐带你去任何地方。
Anytime you feel like singing along, please feel very welcome to do that.
每当您想唱歌时，请非常欢迎这样做。
Kindly limit yourself to the choruses of the song.
请友好地限制自己只在歌曲的合唱部分。
Let me do the verses. It's my show.
让我来写诗句。 这是我的表演。
I mean, all you had to do was be in Colorado somewhere when he would start singing Rocky Mountain High
我的意思是，你只需要在科罗拉多某个地方，他开始唱《Rocky Mountain High》时在那里，
and I'd swear you could feel the whole state rocking.
我发誓你可以感觉整个州在摇摆。
But it's such a fun sounding song and it has such a great guitar lick too. I mean, everybody wanted to play.
但这是一首听起来很有趣的歌曲，而且吉他演奏也很棒。我的意思是，每个人都想演奏。
That's one of the classic, at the time, it was sort of folk rock.
那是经典之一，在当时，它属于一种民谣摇滚。
That song is more than just a pop song, it's now folklore. It's part of our American heritage.
那首歌不仅仅是一首流行歌曲，现在已经成为民间传说。它是我们美国遗产的一部分。
It's a song that's been played for every door.
这是一首为每扇门演奏的歌曲。
When it first came to the mountains, his life was far away on the road, hanging by a song.
当它第一次来到山上时，他的生活在遥远的路途中，依靠一首歌。
But the string's already broken and he doesn't really care.
但琴弦已经断了，他并不真的在乎。
It keeps changing fast and it don't last long.
变化很快，但持续时间不长。
In mid-August, Annie and I and some friends went up to a lake in the high country to watch the meteor showers.
八月中旬，安妮、我和一些朋友去了高山上的一个湖边观看流星雨。
We were right below the tree line, maybe up around 10,500 feet.
我们就在树线下方，也许在10,500英尺左右。
And it was one of those things where you'd stay up all night and watch the meteor showers.
这是你彻夜不眠观看流星雨的事情之一。
Swoosh! A meteor went smoking across the sky.
嗖！ 一颗流星冒着烟划过天空。
It got bigger and bigger until the tail stretched out all the way across the sky and burned itself out.
它变得越来越大，直到尾巴一直延伸到天空中并燃烧出来。
And it was raining fire in the sky.
那是在天上下雨的火。
It was applause and there's the big one and you could hear from different sleeping bags.
那是掌声声中有掌声，你可以听到来自不同睡袋的声音。
Everybody going crazy over this because it's really quite phenomenal if you haven't seen it.
每个人都因为这个而变得疯狂，因为如果你没看过，这真的很不可思议。
Rocky Mountain High
高高的落基山
Decline Cathedral Mountain
衰落大教堂山
I was kind of frightened by the song and that true story about a friend of his who died.
我对这首歌和他死去的朋友的真实故事感到有点害怕。
The song is autobiographical. He sings the truth and that was very important to him.
这首歌是自传体的。 他唱的是真话，这对他来说非常重要。
Annie lost a friend but kept his memory.
安妮失去了一个朋友，但保持了记忆。
Now he walks in quiet solitude, the forest and the streams, taking grace in every step he takes.
现在，他行走在安静的孤独中，漫步在森林和溪流中，迈出的每一步都充满优雅。
His side has turned inside himself to try and understand the serenity of a clear blue mountain plain.
他开始审视自己的内心，试图理解清澈的蓝色山地平原的宁静。
Colorado Rocky Mountain High
科罗拉多高高的落基山
I've seen it rain in fire in the sky.
我看到它在天空中的大火中下雨。
You can talk to God and listen to the casual reply.
您可以与上帝交谈，并听取随意的答复。
Rocky Mountain High
高高的落基山
Now the life is full of wonder but his heart still knows some fear of a simple thing you cannot comprehend.
现在生活充满了奇迹，但他的内心仍然知道对您无法理解的简单事物的恐惧。
Might try to tear the mountains down to bring in a couple more.
可能会尝试将山拆下来，再融入几个。
More people, more scars upon the land.
更多的人，对这片土地造成更多的伤痕
Colorado Rocky Mountain High
科罗拉多高高的落基山
I've seen it rain in fire in the sky.
我见过它在天空中如火般下雨
I know he'd be a poor man if he never saw an eagle fly.
我知道如果他从未看到鹰飞翔，他将是个可怜的人
Rocky Mountain High
高高的落基山
It's a Colorado Rocky Mountain High
这是科罗拉多高高的落基山
I've seen it rain in fire in the sky.
我见过它在天空中如火般下雨
Friends around a campfire everybody's high.
朋友们围坐在篝火旁，大家都很兴奋。
Rocky Mountain High
高高的落基山
Goody Dee
You know when I first started singing I dreamed of moving on from the coffee houses where I was performing and perhaps someday singing in concert halls.
当我第一次开始唱歌时，我梦想着能离开咖啡馆，也许有一天能在音乐厅里唱歌
And maybe if I was lucky I'd be able to take this music and sing around the world in other countries.
也许如果我幸运的话，我能把这种音乐带到世界各地，到其他国家唱歌
Earlier tonight I was here at the Sydney Opera House in Australia.
今晚早些时候，我在澳大利亚的悉尼歌剧院里。
It amazes me.
这让我惊讶。
And you know through it all this has been my closest companion.
你知道在这一切中，这一直是我最亲密的伴侣
And as nice as it is to sing with an orchestra and with a really hot band.
与管弦乐队和一支非常火热的乐队一起唱歌也很好
Well I think that this one belongs to us.
嗯，我认为这首歌属于我们。
Rocky Mountain High
高高的落基山
This old guitar taught me to sing a love song.
这把老吉他教会我怎么唱关于爱情的歌。
It showed me how to laugh, how to cry.
它向我展示了如何笑，如何哭泣。
It introduced me to some friends of mine.
它向我介绍了我的一些朋友。
Brightened up some days.
点亮了生命中的某些日子。
And helped me make it through some lonely nights.
并帮助我度过了一些寂寞的夜晚。
Oh what a friend to have on a cold lonely night.
哦，在寒冷孤独的夜晚有一个朋友真是太好了。
But John was always bigger than life.
但是约翰总是比生活远大。
He was always dreaming big and talking big and thinking big.
他总是怀着远大的梦想，谈论远大的事情，思考远大的事情。
And so there was a real gift to the world around that in his music and in his dreams.
因此，他的音乐和梦想给周围的世界带来了一份真正的礼物。
And I think ultimately they all came true.
而且我认为他们最终都实现了。
I know he's fine and we all miss him.
我知道他很好，我们都想念他。
And it open up the space for us to be.
它为我们打开了空间。
What a lovely place, a lovely space to be.
多么可爱的地方，一个可爱的空间。
This old guitar gave me my life, my living.
这把老吉他给了我的生命，我的生活。
And all the things you know I love to do.
你知道我喜欢做的所有事情。
To serenade the stars that shine from a sunny mountainside.
为阳光明媚的山坡上闪耀的星星唱小夜曲。
Most of all to sing my songs for you.
最重要的是为你唱歌。
I love to sing my songs for you.
我喜欢为你唱歌。
Yes I do you know.
是的，正如你所知。
I love to sing my songs for you.
我喜欢为你唱歌。
John's music has a timeless universal appeal.
约翰的音乐具有永恒的普遍吸引力。
His legacy of peace and compassion for the earth will continue to shine for all of us.
他对地球的和平与同情的遗产将继续为我们所有人发光。
I think that I would most like to be remembered for the fact that I stood up for what I believe in.
我认为我最想记住我为自己所相信的事实而来的事实。
That I spoke for it, I sang for it.
我为此说话，我为此唱歌。
I worked for the things that I believe in.
我为我相信的事情工作。
Good night everybody. Be careful driving home.
晚安各位。小心开车回家。
Be patient with one another.
彼此耐心。
And pray for peace.
并为和平祈祷。
God bless you all and thank you for being with me tonight.
上帝保佑大家，感谢您今晚和我在一起。
Thank you.
谢谢。
I am the home and the blood of my feathers.
我是家园，是我羽毛的血脉。
The time is still burning, they soon will be dry.
时光仍在燃烧，它们将很快变得干燥。
And all those who see me and all who believe in me.
以及所有看到我和所有相信我的人。
There in our freedom I feel when I fly.
当我飞行时，我会感到自由。
Come dance with the west wind.
与西风一起跳舞。
Touch on the mountaintops.
触摸山顶。
Sail over the canyons.
在峡谷上航行。
And up to the stars.
碰到星星。
Reach for the heavens.
到达天堂。
And hope for the future.
并希望未来。
And all that we can see.
以及我们所能看到的一切。
Not what we are.
不是我们。